Hello traders and welcome back to
another episode. In today's lesson,
we'll be talking about fair value
imbalance or inefficiency. These are the
different types of name [music]
people give to what this topic is.
[music]
Let's look at what an imbalance or a
fair value gap is. It means the gap
between the leaks in an impulsive
movement. If price moves rapidly
printing several candles and the weeks
between the candles doesn't meet we say
this is an imbalance or fair value or
inefficience. Now simply we can say
imbalance is an area where there are
only buyers or only sellers. So when
there is an imbalance in the market
price will always come back to fill the
imbalance. Imbalance is essentially
where there has been manipulation and
this has left liquidity behind
within this candle. These are voids in
price which will usually be filled fully
or even halfway. Once filled, price will
then continue in the overall direction.
Imbalance is where there's only one type
of orders in the market. So [music]
there will either be only buys or only
sells [music] at that point. So
basically imbalance means gap between
the weeks. We draw this using the week
to week from [music] the candle to both
sides of the imbalance. How do you then
take advantage of this as a trader? When
[music] the market moves rapidly and
leaves imbalance behind, price usually
fills the creative gap to restore the
balance. Assigning imbalances and
combining them with supply and demand or
other block zones can make you avoid a
lot of entries and can save you from
unnecessary losses. [music]
Now let's look at an example. So this is
an example of an imbalance in price
delivery. Now when price delivering
liquidity from one side to another it is
something behind we call imbalance or
fair value gib
and this usually happens in one order
either in a buy order or in a sell order
you know these big banks [music] anytime
they pushing money into the market they
push a lot of money. So what happens is
that when they push that amount of money
into the market they leave something
behind we call imbalance and definitely
price [music] needs to come back to fill
that imbalance.
This imbalances usually happens between
three candles. [music] Okay. So what
happens is that when the high of the
third candle does [music] not meet with
the low of the first candle then they
need something behind call imbalance. So
when you look around here, we have an
unhealthy price action. You [music] can
see that the low of this candle which is
here this week does not meet with the
high of the candle and it leaves
something in between which [music] we
call the imbalance. Now when you look
here on this side there's a healthy
price action. This imbalance is already
balanced because the high of this candle
has what has not met the low of this
candle. But eventually price came back
to fill that imbalance. So this is what
usually happens. Anytime there is an
imbalance left behind, price need to
come back to fill that imbalance before
the continuation of the mood. It's just
like going to the market to sell or buy.
Once you are selling, you need buyers.
Once you are buying you need sell it. So
when you are selling you need buyers to
come and buy your stuff. This is the
same thing that happens in the forest
market. So this around this area is a
healthy price action because this fair
value gap or imbalance has been filled
with this week. So we had a sell here
and a buy and the buy has filled the
imbalance around this area. But this one
is unhealthy because the weeks has not
met. It's left something behind which is
um the imbalance of fair value. You're
not waiting for price to come back and
feel this imbalance or fair value. Okay.
One thing you should also take note of
is that anytime this imbalances happen
close to either a demand or a supply
zone the probability that price will
come back to that zone is very high
because this demand and supply zone the
imbalances are all in ititional
reference point. So the once this
happens behind an order block where
first orders are taken by the big boys
the probability that price will come
back to fill that imbalance is very
high. So price can come back and fill
the imbalance halfway or fill the
imbalance fully before the continuation
of price.
Let's now go to the chart and look for
an [music] example.
Before we move to the chart, let's talk
about another thing here. Um even though
price came back to feel this imbalance
here. Let's leave this one aside and
talk about this one. You can see that we
have three candles in between. Right
[music]
now you can see that the low of this
candle has met with the high of this
candle. [music] So in between here there
is nothing like an imbalance. This
candle here has met with this one. This
low here you see this candle.
So there is nothing left around this
area. that there's no imbalance left
around sorry there's no imbalance left
around this area so this is what a
healthy price action I have given an
example of this I've alo given an
example of this and then price coming
back to fill that imbalance and also
we've given an example of a single order
which is this [music] one so this low
has met with the high which is the weeks
have met with the wick of the upper
candle So there's nothing like imbalance
left behind unlike this one where the
low has not met with the high of the
third candle. So this is the first
candle. This is the second candle. This
is the third candle [music] and you can
see that the wicks has not met. But this
one the wicks have met. So there's
nothing like imbalance here. This one
price is already balanced. And this one
there is an imbalance. This is also an
[music] imbalanced.
Usually when this happen price might not
come back to this zone [music] any
longer. Okay. But once we have this it
attracts price to come back and fill the
imbalance the same as this. But when
there is a healthy [music] uh price
action which is a balanced um which is
already balanced the probability that
price will not come there is very high.
So this might not attract price to come
back to this zone. [music]
So this is us on the real chart on Euro
USD 4hour time frame. Now you can see
that Euro USD is moving in a downtrend
and at the point this imbalances or fair
value gap you always see them in between
any time you see a an imbalance you see
price coming back to fill that imbalance
and usually that is what usually
happens. If there's an imbalance price
will have to come back and fill. Is this
the same as going to the market when you
are buying you need sellers when you are
selling you need buyers. So at this
point let's look at an example here when
you look at this when you look at what
is happening here you can see that this
this candle is printed by the big boys.
Okay. And then it left something behind
we call imbalance. And I said that
imbalance usually happens between three
candles. So this is the upper candle and
this is the lower candle and the wick of
the upper candle has not met with the
wick of the lower candle. So it left
something behind we call the imbalance.
So in between here is now our imbalance.
This side is now our imbalance. Now what
again do we have? I said that anytime
imbalance is close to a demand or a
supply zone, the probability that price
will come back into that zone before the
move continues again is very high. So at
this [music] point we also have an order
block which is our last candle before
the move to the downside. So this green
candle before the move to the downside
that is now our other block. Let me use
another color. So this now our other
block. Then we also have a fair value
gap. Let me just type this here for you
to [music]
get it. Well,
so we have our supply zone.
Supply zone.
You will always see this happening in
the market. Okay. So, we have our supply
zone here and then we also have our
imbalance LBG
LVG in between
around this area. And now we know that
price is moving in a downtrend. So this
our [music] in between then our supply
zone. Now look at what happened when
price got into the [music]
or the supply. So you see we had price
tapping into the supply zone and then we
had the drop to the downside. So price
has gone up to fill the imbalance. So
this is now a healthy price action.
Initially this is not a healthy price
action because price has not balanced
this year. Now that price has balanced
we now have what a price action. So
immediately price gets there [music]
you start. So this two is now an
institutional reference point. So we did
a first example [music] in a downtrend.
Now we are in an uptrend. And when you
look here, you realize that we had an we
have an imbalance between this candles.
This is the one first candle, second
candles and the third candle. So we have
the first candle here. We also have
[music] the second candle here. And the
low of this candle has not met with the
high of the the first candle at the down
here. So it has left something behind we
call the [music]
SVG. This is very simple to understand.
So this is our imbalance or FVG and we
also have our zone over here which is
our demand zone. So we are waiting for
price to come and balance that uh
imbalance so that we can have a healthy
price action before the continuation to
the upside. So look at what happened
around this area
uh as price was trying to balance that
um imbalance and tapping into the supply
zone. So you can see that when I was
explaining I said that sometime price
will come back and fill it halfway
without tapping into the uh supply or
demand zone. So this area you can see
that immediately the uh how do we call
it the imbalance was filled right at the
moving up. So we didn't even tap into
the demand zone anymore. We only tapped
into the imbalance or LVG and
immediately price started moving up.
That is why I said all these are
institutional reference points which you
have to pay attention to. So this is
what happened after we tapped into the
imbalance. You see price has gone up
from this area and then take our profit
around here. So that is that for
imbalance.
This has brought us to [music] the end
of today's lesson. Hit on the thumbs up
button, [music] subscribe and also leave
a comment below. Now if you're not part
of my telegram channel, I'll leave the
link in the description below. Do what
to join the telegram channel and learn
more or acquire more knowledge from me.
Thank you for watching and see you in
the next video.
[music]